A Finding Aid to the Gaines Ruger Donoho Papers, 1864-1915, in the Archives of American Art AAA.donogain
Archives of American Art
Gaines Ruger Donoho papers
1864-1915
AAA.donogain
Archives of American Art
1 Linear feet
The papers of landscape painter Gaines Ruger Donoho measure a linear foot and date from 1864 to 1915. Found within the papers are certificates of award; invitations and correspondence; a clipping; photographs, including two cyanotypes of Donoho; artwork by Donoho; a wedding dinner sketch in honor of Donoho's wedding signed by 19 friends, including Kenyon Cox and William Merritt Chase; and etchings from other artists, including Adolphe Appian and Maxime Lalanne.
Donoho, Gaines Ruger, 1857-1916
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Gaines Ruger Donoho papers were donated by John R. Hopkins in 1977 via Jane Richards of Hirschl and Adler Galleries in New York.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reel 3667 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Landscape painter Gaines Ruger Donoho (1857-1916) lived and worked in East Hampton, Long Island in New York City. Influenced by the Barbizon School, Donoho studied at the Art Students League with Walter Shirlaw and R. Swain Gifford and studied in Paris from 1879 to 1887. In 1889 he was awarded a silver medal at the University Exposition in Paris and a gold medal at the 1915 Panama Pacific International Exhibition. Donoho married Matilda Ackley Donoho in 1894 and died in New York City in 1916.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Series 1: Gaines Ruger Donoho papers, 1864-1915 (1 linear foot; Box 1, OV 2-4, ODD 5)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of landscape painter Gaines Ruger Donoho measure a linear foot and date from 1864 to 1915. Found within the papers are certificates of award; invitations and correspondence; a clipping; photographs, including two cyanotypes of Donoho; artwork by Donoho; a wedding dinner sketch in honor of Donoho's wedding signed by 19 friends, including Kenyon Cox and William Merritt Chase; and etchings from other artists, including Adolphe Appian and Maxime Lalanne.
Appian, Adolphe, 1818-1898; Lalanne, Maxime, 1827-1886; Landscape painters; Photographs; Printmakers; Prints; Sketches
- Gaines Ruger Donoho Papers, 1864-1915; Series 1; 1 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2-4, ODD 5
  Scope and Contents note
  The Gaines Ruger Donoho papers include certificates of award, including the 1893 Worlds Columbian medal of merit certificate and the 1915 Panama Pacific gold medal certificate; two invitations and two letters; and a clipping. Photographs include two cyanotypes of Donoho, a black and white print of a woman in a wedding gown, and two photographs of artwork by William Stott. Artwork includes graphite, charcoal, and pen and ink sketches of Donoho's work; a wedding dinner sketch in honor of Donoho's wedding in 1894 signed by 19 friends, including Kenyon Cox, William Merritt Chase, Willard Metcalf, and Samuel Isham; and etchings from other artists, including Adolphe Appian, Maxime Lalanne, and Charles Jacque.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are minimally arranged by document type.
  - Certificates of Award, 1893-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in OV 2 and OV 4.
  - Invitations, circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1894-1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clipping, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, circa 1880-1910 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Oversized material housed in OV 3.
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1869-1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Oversized material housed in OV 3 and ODD 5.
  - Photographs, circa 1890-1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 2.
  - Oversized Certificates of Award from Box 1, Folder 1, 1893-1915 (Box OV 2, 4)
  - Oversized Artwork from Box 1, Folder 5, circa 1880-1910 (Box OV 3)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others from Box 1, Folder 6, circa 1869-1910 (Box OV 3)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others from Box 1, Folder 6, circa 1869-1910 (Box ODD 5)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 1, Folder 7, circa 1890-1910 (Box OV 2)